<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Leonard Kioi</title><link>https://lkioi.me/</link><description>Recent content on Leonard Kioi</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 14:11:52 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lkioi.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Pattern Matching in Python</title><link>https://lkioi.me/posts/pattern-matching-python/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 14:11:52 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://lkioi.me/posts/pattern-matching-python/</guid><description>Python 3.10 has introduced Pattern Matching. I&amp;rsquo;ve been eager to try this out for some time now. I first found out about pattern matching when I tried out Elixir lang a while back. Python 3.10 is still pre-release, you can download it here or use asdf to install it.
Let&amp;rsquo;s go through some use-cases which will help in gaining a good grasp of what&amp;rsquo;s possible with pattern matching. In my day job, I use the Django web framework for developing web applications and create RESTful APIs.</description></item><item><title>Python's removesuffix and removeprefix</title><link>https://lkioi.me/posts/python-remove-prefix-suffix/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2021 14:11:52 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://lkioi.me/posts/python-remove-prefix-suffix/</guid><description>Python 3.9 added the string methods removesuffix and removeprefix. When I first saw this I wondered why, since the go-to solution for this is strip, lstrip and rstrip.
On diving into the documentation, I was surprised to find that strip, lstrip and rstrip treat the input chars as a set of characters to remove not a substring. An example will better explain this. Take for example you have the string test_some_stuff and you want to remove the prefix.</description></item><item><title>Named Parameters in Dart, Swift and Python</title><link>https://lkioi.me/posts/named-parameters-in-dart-swift-and-python/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 12:20:58 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://lkioi.me/posts/named-parameters-in-dart-swift-and-python/</guid><description>In software development we optimize for readability since code is read more than its written. Named parameters are one way to improve code readability. Lets say we have a function that calculates the distance between two points. I takes two point Point class instances representing the start and end positions. When calling the functions, using positional arguments its not very clear what is being referred to.
In Python:
In Dart:</description></item><item><title>Running flutter app on Genymotion</title><link>https://lkioi.me/posts/running-flutter-app-on-genymotion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2019 11:41:24 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://lkioi.me/posts/running-flutter-app-on-genymotion/</guid><description>To run flutter apps for android development you have the option of running the app on android studio AVDs or genymotion. I prefer genymotion since I find more lightweight and I can run vagrant boxes usually for the backend of the application. This is not possible with AVDs. Flutter fails to recognize the devices created using genymotion. After searching around the internet I could not find a solution so I&amp;rsquo;m going to post what worked for me.</description></item><item><title>Flutter loading screen with future builder</title><link>https://lkioi.me/posts/flutter-loading-screen-with-future-builder/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2019 10:43:59 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://lkioi.me/posts/flutter-loading-screen-with-future-builder/</guid><description>When developing UIs you need to give the user some feedback on a long running process. A loading widget is normally the go to solution. In React you would have a boolean property in the components state. If for example you are fetching some data from the internet, you would set the boolean to true. In the component&amp;rsquo;s render method you would display a loading widget based on the value of that boolean property.</description></item><item><title>Setting up Dart for local development</title><link>https://lkioi.me/posts/setting-up-dart-for-local-development/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2019 11:23:34 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://lkioi.me/posts/setting-up-dart-for-local-development/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been learning Flutter for mobile development lately. I like the journey so far and I&amp;rsquo;m going to be posting stuff I learn along the way. First i&amp;rsquo;ll show how to setup Dart for local development. I use asdf for managing different versions of language runtimes on my local machine. I found out about it when trying to setup different Python versions. My dev machine comes with Python 3.7 but at work we use Python 3.</description></item><item><title>Get your PRs merged faster</title><link>https://lkioi.me/posts/get-your-prs-merged-faster/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2019 11:21:07 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://lkioi.me/posts/get-your-prs-merged-faster/</guid><description>Every developer wants their code in production as soon as possible. I am assuming you are in a team or at least have someone else to review your code before its merged into staging or production environments. In the past two years I have seen an improvement in the time it takes to get my code merged.
I&amp;rsquo;ve had my PRs waiting for review for days on end. Its annoying to say the least.</description></item><item><title>Improving readability of Python code</title><link>https://lkioi.me/posts/type-hints-in-python/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2018 14:11:52 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://lkioi.me/posts/type-hints-in-python/</guid><description>Readability of code as defined in wikipedia:
In computer programming, readability refers to the ease with which a human reader can comprehend the purpose, control flow, and operation of source code Python is one of the most readable programming languages out there but we can still improve this more by following software development best practises and tools provided by Python core language and the Python community. By software development best practises I am referring to writing clean code.</description></item></channel></rss>