<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>lk</title><link>http://lkioi.me/</link><description>Rants and musings of Leonard Kioi a sofware developer and cycling enthusiast from Nairobi, Kenya</description><atom:link href="http://lkioi.me/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:lenny.kinyanjui.lk@gmail.com"&gt;Leonard Kioi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 11:54:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Justice shall prevail</title><link>http://lkioi.me/posts/justice-shall-prevail/</link><dc:creator>Leonard Kioi</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I feel sad when I think about the corruption in my country. Kenya has so much potential but the looting of public resources has led to so much underdevelopment and suffering. I have been reading the book of Habakkuk for the past few days and i really related to the old testament prophet. In his time, his people were suffering under a foreign power. In my time, my people suffer under corrupt leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Habakkuk 1:2&lt;/code&gt;, he cries to God:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;How long, Lord, must I cry for help? But you do not listen!I call out to you, Violence! But you do not deliver! 
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel the same way, our country has suffered under corrupt leaders, one after the other, scandal after scandal. My heart cries out to God, how long must we suffer under these wicked people who don't care who gets hurt by their actions. They steal from medical funds and money meant for primary school children, they kill directly and indirectly. During the general elections they incite the people to violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Habakkuk 1:4&lt;/code&gt;, he says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Therefore the law is paralyzed,
    and justice never prevails.
The wicked hem in the righteous,
    so that justice is perverted.
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my country, politicians loot public resources, they are charged in court, post bail and leave. The trial begins but no one is ever convicted. They continue to make public appearances and even run for public office again. There is a lack of political will to bring change. Our institutions tasked with fighting corruption seem powerless to do anything. I remember the other day reading an article in one of the local newspapers that the EACC has only recovered 500,000 KES of looted money, yet billions have been stolen. Cases remain in court for years. I remember my mom and her siblings have a case in court for over seven years and its still not done. People can steal and not worry about the consequences, they are able to bribe judges to get favorable sentences. They can bribe court officers so the documents disappear. Justice truly is perverted here. Politics has become so lucrative, people are willing to do anything to anyone so as to get elected or appointed to public office. I had some business dealings with someone and during a casual conversation, I brought up that I was once caught with a traffic offence and was fined in court. He told me if we knew each other then he would have been able to help me, I would have given him &lt;code&gt;ya macho&lt;/code&gt; and walked scott free. He works at the court offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the current DPP, Noordin Haji and the DCI, George Kinoti, they are are ordering arrests and prosecution of high profile individuals. I hope the courts wont let them down. I always remember Haji in my prayers. I need to remember to pray for Kinoti too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Habakkuk 2:3&lt;/code&gt;, God says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;For the revelation awaits an appointed time;
    it speaks of the end
    and will not prove false.
Though it linger, wait for it;
    it[a] will certainly come
    and will not delay.
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reading from &lt;code&gt;2:2&lt;/code&gt; to the end of the chapter, God is passing judgement on the wicked and in &lt;code&gt;2:3&lt;/code&gt; God says it will come to pass. We have the advantage of hindsight, we know the Assyrians were overthrown by the Babylonians so God's word came to pass. In &lt;code&gt;2:9&lt;/code&gt; God specifically speaks to those who build their house by unjust gain. This is our corrupt politicians, corrupt judges, corrupt police officers and anyone else who is corrupt. I believe one day God will bring justice to our country, things will change for our people. Ultimately, all sin will be punished on judgement day so no one will escape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Habakkuk 3:16&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;...
Yet I will wait patiently for the day of calamity
    to come on the nation invading us.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>christianity</category><category>faith</category><category>justice</category><category>kenya</category><guid>http://lkioi.me/posts/justice-shall-prevail/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 09:21:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Improving readability of Python code</title><link>http://lkioi.me/posts/type-hints-in-python/</link><dc:creator>Leonard Kioi</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Readability of code as defined in wikipedia:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;In computer programming, readability refers to the ease with which a human reader can comprehend the purpose,
control flow, and operation of source code
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Python is one of the most readable programming languages out there but we can still improve this more by following software
development best practises and tools provided by Python core language and the Python community. By software development best practises
I am referring to writing clean code. Watch things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use good descriptive variable and function names&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow SOLID priciples&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep functions short&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow coding conventions for your programming language e.g PEP8&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Python, type hinting is also a good option since version 3.5. This will be my main focus for this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article I am only going to refer to tools specific to Python, later I will add another article on SOLID with examples in Python.
Python uses duck typing to determine the type of a variable. This usually leads to criticism where people say it reduces
readability and I agree with them. I have been using Python for the past five years and its annoying having to read a
function body in order know the type of parameters passed in. If its a dictionary passed in or tuple its worse because you
have to look through the code to know the type of keys and values of the &lt;code&gt;dict&lt;/code&gt;. I've had to add print statements to determine
the type being passed in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="codehilitetable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="linenos"&gt;&lt;div class="linenodiv"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;1
2&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;check_status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;project&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;pass&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the code above &lt;code&gt;project&lt;/code&gt; and  &lt;code&gt;date&lt;/code&gt; could be anything. Proper naming of the variables helps but still, &lt;code&gt;project&lt;/code&gt; could
be an &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt;, the project database id or a user defined class instance. &lt;code&gt;date&lt;/code&gt; could be an &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;datetime.date&lt;/code&gt; object.
This is the problem typing module was added to solve. I don't think types within the function body are a huge deal since
you can usually determine this from the context, even in Kotlin you don't have to specify the type when declaring a variable
it can usually be infered from the context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Python's type hints you can specify the parameter being passed to a function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="codehilitetable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="linenos"&gt;&lt;div class="linenodiv"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;.projects&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Project&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;check_status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;project&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Project&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;pass&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm a huge fan of namedtuples, they have a smaller memory footprint compared to classes and are more descriptive that tuples. Typing
takes their descriptiveness to a new level. You can specify the type for the field names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;typing&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;NamedTuple&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;Truck&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;NamedTuple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;num_wheels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;num_axles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>programmming</category><category>python</category><guid>http://lkioi.me/posts/type-hints-in-python/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2018 11:11:52 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>