<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>lk (Posts about kenya)</title><link>http://lkioi.me/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://lkioi.me/categories/kenya.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:lenny.kinyanjui.lk@gmail.com"&gt;Leonard Kioi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 06:45:19 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Tribal hijacking</title><link>http://lkioi.me/posts/tribal-hijacking/</link><dc:creator>Leonard Kioi</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yesterday while casually going through my twitter feed, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JYSexton/status/1137728740535033857"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; post captured my attention. If you have time please go over the thread. It speaks about how Nazi in Germany under Hitler hijacked Christianity. They first identified with it then gradually started distorting it and finally when they had gathered enough of a following cast it aside. Hitler set himself up as a messiah who could not be questioned. This rang with me because I see it at play in my country Kenya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tribe is a good thing. It gives people identity, a sense of belonging. Its something to be proud of. Diversity is a good thing, it makes the country richer in terms of culture. Unfortunately, this has been hijacked by our politicians just like Christianity was in Nazi Germany. Politicians use it to rally support for their own selfish interests. They use the phrase "our people are being targeted" or a variation of it. When  a politician is caught in a corruption scandal, they retreat into their tribal cocoon. Recently, there was a scandal about two dams not being built but money paid for them. As expected, politicians whose names came up said that their people are being targeted. This is just one example that comes to mind but these happens all time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tribe has been poisoned to the extent that there is an underlying anger and resentment towards one another in my country. This boils over when elections come around. People attack one another on social media and defend "their own". People vote for their own even when the politician has a poor track record on development and has been  involved in corruption scandals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to move away from tribal based politics. We need to move towards ideology based politics. I think about the political parties in the USA. When I hear democrats I immediately thinks about the ideas they support and are against not which tribal group they represent. The same thing about Labour party UK. The two major political parties in Kenya, Jubilee and Nasa are largely tribal outfits. The future still looks bleak sadly. The upcoming election seems like will be the largely the same. I pray for change in our thinking as a people. I think the current political elite need to step aside to allow for change just like Ethiopia has done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our current system favors the political elite, so don't expect them to change. It wont happen. I pray there wont be need to spill blood to get change. The people need to rise up and cast aside the shackles of ignorance and embrace the possible future before them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>diversity</category><category>kenya</category><category>tribe</category><guid>http://lkioi.me/posts/tribal-hijacking/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 05:45:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Justice shall prevail</title><link>http://lkioi.me/posts/justice-shall-prevail/</link><dc:creator>Leonard Kioi</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I feel sad when I think about the corruption in my country. Kenya has so much potential but the looting of public resources has led to so much underdevelopment and suffering. I have been reading the book of Habakkuk for the past few days and i really related to the old testament prophet. In his time, his people were suffering under a foreign power. In my time, my people suffer under corrupt leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Habakkuk 1:2&lt;/code&gt;, he cries to God:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;How&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;long&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="nv"&gt;Lord&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="nv"&gt;must&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;I&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;cry&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;help&lt;/span&gt;? &lt;span class="nv"&gt;But&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;listen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;I&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nl"&gt;out&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="nv"&gt;Violence&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;!&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;But&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;deliver&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;!&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I feel the same way, our country has suffered under corrupt leaders, one after the other, scandal after scandal. My heart cries out to God, how long must we suffer under these wicked people who don't care who gets hurt by their actions. They steal from medical funds and money meant for primary school children, they kill directly and indirectly. During the general elections they incite the people to violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Habakkuk 1:4&lt;/code&gt;, he says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Therefore&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;law&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;paralyzed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;justice&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;never&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;prevails&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;The&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;wicked&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;hem&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;righteous&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;so&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;that&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;justice&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;perverted&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my country, politicians loot public resources, they are charged in court, post bail and leave. The trial begins but no one is ever convicted. They continue to make public appearances and even run for public office again. There is a lack of political will to bring change. Our institutions tasked with fighting corruption seem powerless to do anything. I remember the other day reading an article in one of the local newspapers that the EACC has only recovered 500,000 KES of looted money, yet billions have been stolen. Cases remain in court for years. I remember my mom and her siblings have a case in court for over eighteen years and its still not done. People can steal and not worry about the consequences, they are able to bribe judges to get favorable sentences. They can bribe court officers so the documents disappear. Justice truly is perverted here. Politics has become so lucrative, people are willing to do anything to anyone so as to get elected or appointed to public office. I had some business dealings with someone and during a casual conversation, I brought up that I was once caught with a traffic offence and was fined in court. He told me if we knew each other then he would have been able to help me, I would have given him &lt;code&gt;ya macho&lt;/code&gt; and walked scott free. He works at the court offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the current DPP, Noordin Haji and the DCI, George Kinoti, they are are ordering arrests and prosecution of high profile individuals. I hope the courts wont let them down. I always remember Haji in my prayers. I need to remember to pray for Kinoti too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Habakkuk 2:3&lt;/code&gt;, God says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;For&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;revelation&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;awaits&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;an&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;appointed&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;time&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;it&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;speaks&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;will&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;prove&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;.
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Though&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;it&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;linger&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="k"&gt;wait&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;it&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;it&lt;/span&gt;[&lt;span class="nv"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;] &lt;span class="nv"&gt;will&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;certainly&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;come&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;will&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;not&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;delay&lt;/span&gt;.
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reading from &lt;code&gt;2:2&lt;/code&gt; to the end of the chapter, God is passing judgement on the wicked and in &lt;code&gt;2:3&lt;/code&gt; God says it will come to pass. We have the advantage of hindsight, we know the Assyrians were overthrown by the Babylonians so God's word came to pass. In &lt;code&gt;2:9&lt;/code&gt; God specifically speaks to those who build their house by unjust gain. This is our corrupt politicians, corrupt judges, corrupt police officers and anyone else who is corrupt. I believe one day God will bring justice to our country, things will change for our people. Ultimately, all sin will be punished on judgement day so no one will escape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Habakkuk 3:16&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;...
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;Yet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;I&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;will&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;wait&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;patiently&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;day&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;calamity&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;come&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;on&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;nation&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;invading&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;us&lt;/span&gt;.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>christianity</category><category>faith</category><category>justice</category><category>kenya</category><guid>http://lkioi.me/posts/justice-shall-prevail/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 09:21:45 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>