<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>python on Leonard Kioi</title><link>https://lkioi.me/tags/python/</link><description>Recent content in python on Leonard Kioi</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 14:11:52 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lkioi.me/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Pattern Matching in Python</title><link>https://lkioi.me/posts/pattern-matching-python/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2021 14:11:52 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://lkioi.me/posts/pattern-matching-python/</guid><description>Python 3.10 has introduced Pattern Matching. I&amp;rsquo;ve been eager to try this out for some time now. I first found out about pattern matching when I tried out Elixir lang a while back. Python 3.10 is still pre-release, you can download it here or use asdf to install it.
Let&amp;rsquo;s go through some use-cases which will help in gaining a good grasp of what&amp;rsquo;s possible with pattern matching. In my day job, I use the Django web framework for developing web applications and create RESTful APIs.</description></item><item><title>Python's removesuffix and removeprefix</title><link>https://lkioi.me/posts/python-remove-prefix-suffix/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2021 14:11:52 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://lkioi.me/posts/python-remove-prefix-suffix/</guid><description>Python 3.9 added the string methods removesuffix and removeprefix. When I first saw this I wondered why, since the go-to solution for this is strip, lstrip and rstrip.
On diving into the documentation, I was surprised to find that strip, lstrip and rstrip treat the input chars as a set of characters to remove not a substring. An example will better explain this. Take for example you have the string test_some_stuff and you want to remove the prefix.</description></item><item><title>Named Parameters in Dart, Swift and Python</title><link>https://lkioi.me/posts/named-parameters-in-dart-swift-and-python/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 12:20:58 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://lkioi.me/posts/named-parameters-in-dart-swift-and-python/</guid><description>In software development we optimize for readability since code is read more than its written. Named parameters are one way to improve code readability. Lets say we have a function that calculates the distance between two points. I takes two point Point class instances representing the start and end positions. When calling the functions, using positional arguments its not very clear what is being referred to.
In Python:
In Dart:</description></item><item><title>Improving readability of Python code</title><link>https://lkioi.me/posts/type-hints-in-python/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2018 14:11:52 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://lkioi.me/posts/type-hints-in-python/</guid><description>Readability of code as defined in wikipedia:
In computer programming, readability refers to the ease with which a human reader can comprehend the purpose, control flow, and operation of source code Python is one of the most readable programming languages out there but we can still improve this more by following software development best practises and tools provided by Python core language and the Python community. By software development best practises I am referring to writing clean code.</description></item></channel></rss>